<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Look Think Make</title><link href="http://www.elfnor.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.elfnor.com/feeds/food.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.elfnor.com/</id><updated>2017-01-29T22:00:00+13:00</updated><entry><title>Sugar-Free Fermented Marmalade</title><link href="http://www.elfnor.com/sugar-free-fermented-marmalade.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-29T22:00:00+13:00</published><updated>2017-01-29T22:00:00+13:00</updated><author><name>elfnor</name></author><id>tag:www.elfnor.com,2017-01-29:sugar-free-fermented-marmalade.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="feremented marmalade" src="/images/REC-citrus.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After making &lt;a href="http://www.elfnor.com/preserved-lemons.html"&gt;preserved lemons&lt;/a&gt; I saw a comment somewhere that marmalade was once made by lacto-fermentation rather than with heaps of sugar like jam. I prefer a low sugar, low glycemic index diet so I made up the concoction below. Later I searched on-line for &lt;a href="http://www.culturesforhealth.com/learn/recipe/lacto-fermentation-recipes/lacto-fermented-orange-marmalade/"&gt;recipes&lt;/a&gt; and found most of them make a sweeter cooked product. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This recipe is tangy and salty and dosen't have the jelly consistency of a cooked marmalade. It's wonderful on sour-dough bread and also makes a great ingredient in a chicken or pork marinade. It can also be used in baking in place of candied/crystallized orange peel. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sugar-free-feremented-marmalade"&gt;Sugar-Free Feremented Marmalade&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Makes 1 600 ml jar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1-2 lemons&lt;br /&gt;
1-2 oranges&lt;br /&gt;
1-2 mandarins&lt;br /&gt;
1-2 t salt  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find a ~600 ml glass jar with a wider mouth and another small glass jar that fits neatly inside the mouth of the large jar. Clean both jars inside and out. Find something to weigh down the small jar with. I use glass marbles. See the &lt;a href="http://www.elfnor.com/preserved-lemons.html"&gt;preserved lemons&lt;/a&gt; post for a diagram of the airlock setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cut all the citrus fruit into small pieces. Place the chopped fruit into the jar in layers sprinkling some of the salt on each layer and pressing each layer down with a spoon or pestle until the juices run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the jar is almost full push the small jar into the large jar so that all the fruit pieces are held under the juice. The juice should come part way up the outside of the small jar. Add some weight to the small jar to keep it in place. All this minimizes the surface area exposed to the air and the potential for mould. Put the large jar into a bowl to contain any overflow and cover everything with a plastic bag to keep it all clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leave to ferment in a warm place (20 &amp;deg;C to 30 &amp;deg;C) for about three weeks (many on-line recipes only ferment for a few days but the raw fruit needs a little longer to soften), the mixture should bubble after the first few days. Any overflow juice can be used in cooking. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 3 weeks the fruit should have changed texture and be a lot softer. Put a lid on the large jar and store in the fridge. The marmalade should keep for months. Stir occasionally to keep the top layer under the salty juice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recipes that use this: (links added as I write them)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;White Chocolate Truffles &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar recipes: (links added as I write them)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.elfnor.com/preserved-lemons.html"&gt;preserved lemons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="make"></category><category term="food"></category></entry><entry><title>Preserved Lemons</title><link href="http://www.elfnor.com/preserved-lemons.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-13T22:00:00+13:00</published><updated>2017-01-13T22:00:00+13:00</updated><author><name>elfnor</name></author><id>tag:www.elfnor.com,2017-01-13:preserved-lemons.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="preserved lemons" src="/images/REC-lemons.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without my own lemon tree, supermarket lemons are expensive so I go to the Farmers' market and get a large bag and make preserved lemons. When I first made these I didn't realize they were supposed to ferment and was a bit worried by the bubbling. When I use fresh lemons often I use only the juice or the thin outer rind. With the preserved lemons all of the lemon including the white part of the skin gets used. The lemons and juice are a little salty for sweet dishes but are awesome in stir-fries, stews, marinades, dressings, and kale salads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="preserved-lemons"&gt;Preserved Lemons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Makes 1 600 ml jar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6-10 lemons&lt;br /&gt;
2 t salt  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find a ~600 ml glass jar with a wider mouth and another small glass jar that fits neatly inside the mouth of the large jar. Clean both jars inside and out. Find something to weigh down the small jar with. I use glass marbles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cut the lemons into quarters long ways. Most recipes say to only cut them part way through but they go into the jar better if cut all the way through. Pack into the large jar sprinkling in salt with each layer. Use a spoon or a large pestle to pack the lemons down squeezing out the juice. Continue until the jar is mostly full. The lemon juice should cover the lemon pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Push the small jar into the large jar so that all the lemon pieces are held under the juice. The juice should come part way up the outside of the small jar. Add some weight to the small jar to keep it in place. All this minimizes the surface area exposed to the air and the potential for mould. Put the large jar into a bowl to contain any overflow and cover everything with a plastic bag to keep it all clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leave to ferment in a warm place (20 &amp;deg;C to 30 &amp;deg;C) for about three weeks, the mixture should bubble after the first few days. Any overflow juice can be used in cooking. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 3 weeks the lemon skins should have changed texture and be softer and tastier. Put a lid on the large jar and store in the fridge. The lemons should keep for months. Stir occasionally to keep the lemon pieces under the salty juice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ferment lock" src="/images/REC-ferment_air_lock.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recipes that use this: (links added as I write them)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chicken Liver Pate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar recipes: (links added as I write them)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.elfnor.com/sugar-free-fermented-marmalade.html"&gt;Fermented Marmalade&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="make"></category><category term="food"></category></entry><entry><title>Fermented Chili and Garlic sauce</title><link href="http://www.elfnor.com/fermented-chili-and-garlic-sauce.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-06T22:00:00+13:00</published><updated>2017-01-06T22:00:00+13:00</updated><author><name>elfnor</name></author><id>tag:www.elfnor.com,2017-01-06:fermented-chili-and-garlic-sauce.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="chili sauce" src="/images/REC-chilli-saucce.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many cultures (Louisiana, Thai,  Hunan, Korea, Indonesia, Portugal) make a fermented chili sauce. This is my goto recipe and there's always a jar of this in the fridge. I'm not into fuzzy things like straining it after fermenting preferring the chunky taste surprise. I don't add extra flavorings like ginger or lemon grass as the plain version is more versatile. The fresh red pepper makes sure there are some wild lacto bugs to start the ferment and reduces the heat a little. Feel free to increase the mild pepper to chili ratio for a milder sauce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of fermenting books and sites suggest you need a special type of salt. I use the table salt I have in the cupboard which is iodized sea salt. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chili sauce is addictive, before you know it you'll be eating it on toast for breakfast or adding it to chocolate fudge. The fermenting process takes some of the hard edge of the chili flavor while losing none of the heat. I also reckon it reduces after burn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="fermented-chili-and-garlic-sauce"&gt;Fermented Chili and Garlic sauce&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Makes 1 300 ml jar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;200 g frozen red chilies&lt;br /&gt;
3 cloves garlic&lt;br /&gt;
1 large red mild pepper chopped stem removed&lt;br /&gt;
2 t salt  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blend everything and scoop into a clean jar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover the jar with a  clean cloth and and hold in place with a rubber band.  Leave to ferment in a warm place (20 &amp;deg;C to 30 &amp;deg;C) for at least a week (up to three weeks) - stirring every day - the mixture should bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When done stir in 1.5 T of vinegar and keep in fridge. Stir each time you use it. It should last several months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recipes that use this: (links added as I write them)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chili Chocolate Fudge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chicken Liver Pate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="make"></category><category term="food"></category></entry></feed>