<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Look Think Make</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/look.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2014-01-28T22:00:00+13:00</updated><entry><title>Software for managing (e)books</title><link href="/software-for-managing-ebooks.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-28T22:00:00+13:00</updated><author><name>elfnor</name></author><id>tag:,2014-01-28:software-for-managing-ebooks.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Adding the links to the &lt;a href="/reading-lists.html"&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, I realised I'd dropped a lot of names of bits of software I use into the post. Here's a list with an explanation of what I do with each:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.readerware.com"&gt;Readerware&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href="http://www.readerware.com"&gt;http://www.readerware.com&lt;/a&gt;
We use this to keep a computer list of the paper books we own. This is both for interest - it's faster to search the database than to search the shelves - and for insurance purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add books to Readerware you only need to enter ISBN numbers rather than the whole author, title etc. The software then looks the ISBN up on line and downloads information on the book including the tile, author, synopsis, cover etc. The initial entry of the majority of our books was done with a cuecat bar-code scanner. With this you scan the book's bar-code, the software converts this to an ISBN and then looks up the books details from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Readerware is commercial software and these days I'd probably choose an open source alternative like &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/"&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;‎. I use Zotero mostly for pdfs of scientific papers but it can do books via ISBN.  &lt;a href="http://www.datacrow.net"&gt;Datacrow&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://tellico-project.org/"&gt;Tellico&lt;/a&gt; also look to have similar functionality to Readerware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related: I have used &lt;a href="http://griffith.cc"&gt;Griffith&lt;/a&gt; which is a similar open source program for cataloging DVD collections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.dotepub.com"&gt;dotEPUB&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href="http://www.dotepub.com"&gt;http://www.dotepub.com&lt;/a&gt;
DotEPUB works as a bookmarklet (a bookmark with some javascript code included) that you add to the bookmark bar or list in your browser. On a web page click the dotEPUB bookmarklet and the main text from the page is saved as an epub or mobi to transfer to your ereader. dotEPUB strips a lot of the extras (including images) from the page for a nice clean ebook. This is great for on-line short stories or long articles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.grabmybooks.com"&gt;grabmybooks&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href="http://www.grabmybooks.com"&gt;http://www.grabmybooks.com&lt;/a&gt;
Grabmybooks works similarly to dotEPUB but is installed as an extension in Firefox. It allows more control over which part of the web page is grabbed and handles pages with lots of images well. It allows for multiple web pages to be grabbed as separate articles or chapters to one book. This is great for how-to articles, or for capturing someone's page of links to their best web reads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With grabmybooks you can also edit the ebook or add more articles to it from within firefox. On its own it saves in the epub format, if you have calibre (see below) installed you can also save your ebook in the mobi format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a number of other similar services around including &lt;a href="http://getpocket.com/‎"&gt;Pocket&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href="https://www.readability.com"&gt;Readability&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href="http://www.instapaper.com/"&gt;Instapaper&lt;/a&gt; but these all require you to create an account with the provider. This seems a bit invasive but come with web storage, web syncing and social media type functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://calibre-ebook.com/"&gt;Calibre&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href="http://calibre-ebook.com/"&gt;http://calibre-ebook.com/&lt;/a&gt;
Calibre is open source software for managing ebook collections. It is also good at converting between ebook formats, epub to mobi, or even docx or pdf to mobi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calibre handles syncing between the ebook collection on your PC and the files on your ebook and includes an ebook viewer that can handle lots of formats. I store all my bought ebooks, and those created with grabmybooks and dotEPUB in calibre. You can also add user fields to the database which I'm using to classify the authors by country and gender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/"&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;‎- &lt;a href="http://www.zotero.org/"&gt;http://www.zotero.org/&lt;/a&gt;
Zotero is an amazing open source tool for managing research papers. It can also be used for managing many types of media. It installs as a firefox extension or as a plug-in plus standalone app for other browsers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When on a web page that lists papers, zotero provides an icon to click to save all the info (metadata) on the paper to your zotero database. You can also save the full pdf of the paper to your database/library. The database can be  searched on the full pdf text. The bibliographic reference part of a paper you are writing can easily be generated in any style needed from either within the zotero app or using plug-ins for open-office or word. If you have a pdf file you've downloaded separately, zotero can search it for meta-data and add it to your database as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above describes how I use zotero for managing scientific papers but it can be used for almost any type of file or to save web pages off line.  Have a look at its website for a heap more features including on line syncing of your library, adding notes to papers, or sharing a library of papers amongst a group of users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there's a few ways to help with taming the ereading pile.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="ebook"></category><category term="reading"></category></entry><entry><title>Reading Lists</title><link href="/reading-lists.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-26T22:00:00+13:00</updated><author><name>elfnor</name></author><id>tag:,2014-01-26:reading-lists.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I love to read and reading lists fascinate me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought a Kindle ereader in 2011 and its resulted in some large changes in my reading habits. I own a lot of paper books, there's 1300+ in the house according to our &lt;a href="http://www.readerware.com"&gt;Readerware&lt;/a&gt; database (databases are even fancier lists), but pre ereader most of what I read came from the local library. Every three weeks I'd come back with a pile of 6 to 8 books, at least one non-fiction and one book for looking at (art, craft photography). I'd look on the recently returned shelves, the books the librarians had put on display, and keep a special look out for local authors and witers outside the WEIRD (western, educated, industrialised, rich, democratic). So there was a lot of serendipity in what I bought home. I don't think I've been back to the library since I got the ereader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post Kindle, the choice of potential books is huge. Not just from amazon.com. I also make use of &lt;a href="http://www.dotepub.com"&gt;dotepub&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://grabmybooks.com"&gt;grabmybooks&lt;/a&gt; to make copies of online short stories and blogs to read later. This large choice has a downside in that I'm sure&lt;em&gt; I now read less local authors and more in the science fiction fantasy (sff) genre than previously. The upside is that if I hear about a book then I can be reading it that day&lt;/em&gt;*.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading lists can be about what someone else thinks you should read (eg. "The Western Canon") or about challenges to change what or how much you read. This blogger's project &lt;a href="http://ayearofreadingtheworld.com"&gt;http://ayearofreadingtheworld.com&lt;/a&gt; where she read one book from each of the 196 countries in one year and her previus project &lt;a href="http://ayearofreadingwomen.wordpress.com/"&gt;http://ayearofreadingwomen.wordpress.com/&lt;/a&gt; really inspire me to widen my reading. Being a data freak and a rule bender I'm in the process of going through my ebook collection (stored in &lt;a href="http://calibre-ebook.com/"&gt;Calibre&lt;/a&gt; - more lists) and tagging the books with the author's country and gender. Any countries I've already bagged in the last year (maybe two years) I'll discount from the 196. After that I'm going to try and fill in the rest not with full novels but as many short stories as possible, preferably ones avaliable online so I can share. I'm sure my bias to sff will prevail and I'll also try for a 50/50 male/female split.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*I think if I log on the the local library site I can download a copy of my borrowing history (more lists) and do a comparison of pre and post ereader reading. No, too geeky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Most books. I'll write a post soon about the odd gaps in availability of ebooks for non-USA customers on amazon.com. Also the differences in pricing and how to set up a proxy server on the amazon e3 cloud to help with these issues.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="ebook"></category><category term="reading"></category></entry></feed>